Guide to the National Organization for Women, New York City Chapter (NOW-NYC) Records TAM.106
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records
1966-ongoing
1966-1984
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Organization for Women. New York City
TAM.106
98.25 Linear Feet in 82 record cartons, 28 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 8 oversize flat boxes, 1 artifact box, 2 oversize folders, and 4 folders in a shared flat box
2 websites in 2 archived website.
Betty Friedan founded the National Organization for Women in Washington, D.C. in 1966 to "bring women into the mainstream of American society." Not long after, the national organization was formed and the New York Chapter was founded in 1967. The collection includes: board, membership and committee minutes, officers' files, treasurer's reports, resumes, chapter newsletters, committee newsletters, newspapers, press clippings, photocopies of articles, pamphlets, film scripts, audio recordings, photographs, negatives, slides, flyers, leaflets, posters, membership lists, press releases, government publications, court decisions, financial statements, magazines, and an archived version of the New York chapter website, http://nownyc.org/. The website was first captured in October 2007. The material deals extensively with women's image in the media, divorce, abortion and feminist groups in NYC. Other subject files include child care, legislation and politics. Correspondents include: Bella Abzug, Martha Griffins, Gloria Steinem, Patsy Mink, Edward Muskie, Ed Koch, George McGovern, John Dean III, Jacob Javits, Shirley Chisholm and John Brademas.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by NOW-NYC, 1978, 1981-1993, 2008, 2012, 2018, and 2023. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1981.007, 1981.008, 1981.010, 2008.062, 2012.069, 2018.019, and 2023.097.
Materials found in the repository were added to the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with these materials is 2014.054.
In 2015, 2 additional boxes of photographs and artifacts found in repository were incorporated into the collection. The accession numbers associated with this material are NPA 2000.216, NPA 2000.232, and NPA 2001.023.
In 2017, materials were found in repository. These materials had been separated from the original collection during processing. Materials were reincorporated into the collection in 2017. The accession numbers associated with these materials are NPA 2000.208 and NPA 2000.209.
NOW-NYC sent an additional donation of legal briefs and executive board meetings minutes in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.042. In 2018 the organization sent an additional 5 boxes of photographs, videos, and memorabilia. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.019. NOW-NYC sent addition administrative documents and ephemera in July 2023; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.097.
https://nownyc.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Other Left Activism Web Archive. In 2014, http://nownyc-notcool.tumblr.com/ was added. In November 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In February 2022, 7 Google Documents related to the 2021 Manhattan District Attorney candidates were added to Archive-it to better capture these materials directly. The accession numbers associated with these websites are 2022.043.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Some recordings from Series XI: Radio Recordings, Symposiums and Conferences are missing as of October 2019, and are therefore not available to researchers.
Historical Note
In 1966, Betty Friedan founded the National Organization for Women in Washington, D.C., a group whose goal was to "bring women into the mainstream of American society." Three years earlier, her book The Feminine Mystique had hit a nerve with American women (largely white, upper class women), whose discontent with their economic and social opportunities would result in the feminist social activism of the 1960s and 1970s. Not long after the national organization was formed, the New York Chapter was founded in 1967. It was the founding chapter and, arguably in its early days, the most influential chapter, as its victories in New York rippled out into the rest of the country. The motivating force for its early organizing efforts was largely related to employment discrimination in hiring practices and discrepancy in wages between men and women--one of NOW-N.Y.C.'s early victories was the elimination of sex-segregated help-wanted advertisements in the New York Times. However, from its inception, the group was multi-issue, functioning through a committee structure that included committees on the arts, child care, education, employment, the image of women in the media, legislation and politics, reproductive rights, and sexuality.
NOW-N.Y.C. sponsored large-scale marches and strikes, such as the well-known "Women Strike for Equality" march August 26, 1970 in New York City, which became an annual event for NOW for several years. Early on the group focused on media-attention-getting tactics to make its relatively small ranks look larger, such as the "flush-in" outside the offices of Colgate-Palmolive to protest discrimination in hiring practices. The organization also used such mainstream democratic tactics as lobbying legislators, collecting petitions, and sending mass mailings to the White House to put pressure on government officials. The chapter participated in an annual state lobby day with NOW-New York State. In the 1980s, NOW created a group called WomanPower PAC, a political action committee formed to raise money to elect women and feminist leaders to elected office. The first four presidents of NOW-NYC were Jean Faust, Ti Grace Atkinson, Ivy Bottini and Jacqueline Ceballos (the latter in 1971).
The Education Committee studied the course offerings of girls and boys in New York public schools in the 1970s, and its report was so much in demand, it went into four printings. New York schools and schools across the country began changing their course offerings as a result of this committee's work. In the mid-seventies it began addressing the issue of rape, and its Rape Prevention Committee was one of the first of its kind, offering myriad services to victims of rape and battery and changing the public perception of rape and rape victims. In the late 1970s and 1980s, NOW-N.Y.C.'s employment focus broadened to include career-training workshops and referral services for employers.
The struggle for passage of the Equal Rights Amendment began in the early 1970s and gained momentum throughout the decade. In the years before the deadline for ratification, the issue took center stage for NOW-N.Y.C., and the ERA Committee reached out to other states to aid in the battles for ratification in state legislatures. In the areas of the arts and the image of women in the media, NOW fought for a dignified representation of women. The group's Image Committee influenced changes in print media advertising, and the Arts Committee called attention to the discrimination against women in the art world. The organization continues its mission of equality for women in New York City. For information on the actions, events, and tactics of the committees, please see the descriptions below each committee heading.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes material from 1966 to 2019. The bulk of the collection consists of the committee files for these years, as most of the National Organization for Women- New York City's (NOW-NYC) actions and events were planned through its committees. Materials in the collection include but are not limited to the following: announcements, ballots, brochures, bylaws, calendars, clippings, correspondence, depositions, flyers, forms, invitations, job descriptions, leaflets, legislative bills, lists, memoranda, minutes, mission statements, petitions, poems, position papers, press kits, print advertisements, programs, reports, resolutions, resumes, schedules, songs, speeches, voting records. Collection also includes audio cassettes of meetings and conferences, film, video, photographs, negatives, artifacts, posters, and ephemera. The collection also includes an archived version of the New York chapter website, http://nownyc.org/, which was first captured in 2007. The website includes information on the latest news and events regarding NOW-NYC, their priorities, and ways to get involved.
The collection also contains legal briefs from the late 1990s related to NOW-NYC work in support of women in New York State who faced work-place discrimination and sexual harassment.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in fifteen series, two of which have been further arranged in subseries. The contents of most series are arranged alphabetically, with several exceptions. Series II: Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Series VI: National and Regional NOW is arranged by chapter or region and arranged from largest organizing group to smallest. Records are arranged chronologically with each organizing body. Legal briefs in Series XIII: Legal Cases are arranged in rough grouping by case. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: Administration
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Officers' Files
Subseries A: Jean Faust, 1966-1970
Subseries B: Elayne Snyder, 1971-1975
Subseries C: Noreen Connell, 1968-1972
Series IV: Committees
Series V: Programs
Series VI: National and Regional NOW
Series VII: NOW and other Organizations
Series VIII: Photographs, Slides, Graphics, Ephemera and Other Materials
Subseries A: Photographs and Negatives
Subseries B: "Our North American Foremothers" Slideshow
Subseries C: Graphics, Ephemera and Other Material
Series IX: Artifacts and Oversize Ephemera
Series X: Audio/Visual Materials
Series XI: Radio Records, Symposiums, and Conferences
Series XII: Audiovisual Materials
Series XIII: Legal Cases
Series XIV: Unprocessed Materials
Series XV: Archived Website.
Separated Materials
Newsletters and newspapers have been removed from the collection and housed in the Tamiment Library's serials collection. They fall into the following categories: National NOW newsletters; NOW Regional newsletters (East, West, etc.); NOW--New York State newsletters; Local chapters of NOW (excluding NOW New York Chapter); NOW New York Chapter newsletters; NOW New York Chapter committee newsletters.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Press releases.; 16mm; Résumés (personnel records); Reports.; Contact sheets.; Day care centers -- United States.; Abortion -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Negatives (photographic); New York (N.Y.).; Feminism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographic prints.; Posters.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Women -- Political activity -- United States.; Women -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Scripts (documents); Slides (photographs); Women's rights -- New York (State) -- New York.; Chisholm, Shirley, 1924-2005; Brademas, John, 1927-2016; Steinem, Gloria; WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.); Abzug, Bella S., 1920-1998; Dean, John W. (John Wesley), 1938-; Griffins, Martha; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; Koch, Ed, 1924-2013; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012; Mink, Patsy T., 1927-2002; Muskie, Edward; National Organization for Women. New York City
- Series I: Administration, 1967-2019
  Scope and Contents note
  The structure of the chapter is as follows. The Executive Committee consists of the officers (president, vice president, secretary, treasurer). The Board of Directors consists of officers and standing committee coordinators. The Advisory Council is an administrative committee whose purpose is to assist with fund raising and chapter development. The Elections Committee is an administrative committee whose purpose is to organize and conduct elections. The bulk of these files are the minutes of the Board of Directors (called the Executive Board in 1970 and 1971) and the Executive Committee. Election Committee folders contain ballots, flyers, minutes, officers' lists, and procedures statements. Also included are files on such things as by-laws, calendars, office information, parliamentary procedure, and job descriptions.
  - Advisory Committee--Child Care Meeting, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Action Alert Mailings, 2000-2001 (Box 105, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Council, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors Minutes: Part 1, Jan 1989 - Aug 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes: Part 2, Jan 1989 - Aug 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, Sept 1989 - Dec 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes: Part 1, Jan 1990 - Nov 1990 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes: Part 2, Jan 1990 - Nov 1990 (Box 1A, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1999-2005 (Box 45, Box 46)
  - Board, Service Fund: Minutes, 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 6)
  - Bylaws, 1967-1978 (Box 1A, Folder 7)
  - Calendars, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Calendars, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Charter, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Contract [Labor] District 65 UAW and NOW NYC, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3A, Box 1)
  - Coordinators Rap, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Council Meetings, 1987-1989 (Box 103, Folder 1-2)
  - Council Meetings, 1990 (Box 103, Folder 3)
  - Council Meetings, 1991-1992 (Box 103, Folder 4-5)
  - Council Meetings, 1993-1996 (Box 103, Folder 6)
  - Council Meetings, 1997 (Box 104, Folder 1-2)
  - Council Meetings, 1998 (Box 104, Folder 3-4)
  - Council Meetings, 1999-2002 (Box 104, Folder 5-6)
  - Council Meetings, 2006 (Box 104, Folder 7)
  - Council Meetings, 2007 (Box 104, Folder 8-9)
  - Election Committee, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Election Committee, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Election Committee, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Election Committee, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Election Committee, 1975-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Job Descriptions, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Leases/Permits, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Newsletter, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - NOW Center Guidelines, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Office Information, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Parliamentary Procedure, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 2000-2002 (Box 104, Folder 11, Box 105, Folder 1)
  - Referrals, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Resumes, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Speakers Bureau, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Speakers Bureau, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Telephone Surveys, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "What NOW" Newsletters, 2005-2011 (Box 104, Folder 10)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1966-1982
  Scope and Content Note
  Most of the correspondence is included in the series described below. General correspondence that does not pertain to a specific committee is located in this series. Included is Muriel Fox's historic 1966 press release announcing the formation of NOW. The 1973 folder includes material pertaining to the debate between NOW and Anne Grant over the holder of the copyright for the 1972 slide presentation, "Our North American Foremothers." The 1975 folder documents the internal controversy that took place at the NOW national conference in New Orleans in December 1974. Materials include letters and memoranda.
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series III: Officers' Files
  - Subseries A: Jean Faust, 1966-1970
    Jean Faust served as NOW-N.Y.C.'s first president in 1967. Notable in her papers is information on the action taken against Colgate-Palmolive in 1967 for discrimination in hiring practices--members Flo Kennedy, Jacqui Ceballos, and Kate Millet led a "flush-in" in front of company headquarters in New York, dumping the company's products into a commode on Park Avenue. Also included are files on the 1967 New York State Constitutional Convention, where NOW demanded many legislative changes to promote equality of opportunity in education, employment, and housing. Materials on the actions to desegregate the classified advertisements of the New York Times appear here as well. These files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Materials include announcements, bylaws, correspondence, flyers, mailing lists, meeting notices, print media articles, reports.
    - Jean Faust--Abortion, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Jean Faust--By-laws, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Jean Faust--Colgate-Palmolive, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Jean Faust--Constitutional Convention--Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Jean Faust--Constitutional Convention--Delegates, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jean Faust--Constitutional Convention--Statements (on #449 and #450), 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jean Faust--Constitutional Convention--Proposals, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Jean Faust--Correspondence (April-August 1967), 1967-24685 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Jean Faust--Correspondence (Sept.-Dec. 1967) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Jean Faust--Correspondence, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Jean Faust--Correspondence, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Jean Faust--Correspondence, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Jean Faust--Education Report--Kate Millet, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Jean Faust--EEOC Correspondence--Classified Ad Project, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Jean Faust--Employment Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Jean Faust--Equal Rights for Indian Women, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Jean Faust--First Officers, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Jean Faust--Henrietta Levenson, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Jean Faust--Human Rights--NY State Governor's Commission, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Jean Faust--Image of Women in Media, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Jean Faust--Information Packet, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Jean Faust--Legislation, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Jean Faust--Legislative--Political, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Jean Faust--Mailing List, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Jean Faust--Meeting Notices, Minutes, etc., 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Jean Faust--NOW-NY on Radio and TV, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Jean Faust--OFCC, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Jean Faust--Pauline Dziob Case, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Jean Faust--Pauline Sharfstein, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Jean Faust--Print Media Articles, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Jean Faust--Reports, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Jean Faust--Sex Education, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Subseries B: Elayne Snyder, 1971-1975
    Elayne Snyder was president of NOW-N.Y.C. in 1974. At that time, NOW-N.Y.C. sponsored a series of programs to celebrate women in the arts, which were held at Town Hall in 1974. Her papers contain materials from most of the committees active at this time period as well as administrative records from the Executive Committee and National NOW as well. Snyder's papers are arranged alphabetically by topic. Materials include announcements, brochures, correspondence, programs, flyers, minutes, and position statements.
    - Elayne Snyder--Ad Hoc Committees, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Elayne Snyder--Advisory Council, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Elayne Snyder--Arts, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Elayne Snyder--Board of Directors, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Elayne Snyder--Child Care, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Elayne Snyder--Education, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Elayne Snyder--Education, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Elayne Snyder--Election Procedure, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Elayne Snyder--Employment Committee, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)